Emma L. Alexander

MPHys (Hons), PhD, FRAS, AFHEA | RESEARCH ASSOCIATE IN RADIO ASTRONOMY

Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, Department of Physics and Astronomy, The University of Manchester Alan Turing Building, Oxford Road, Manchester, M13 9PL

Profile

Astrophysicist working within radio astronomy and polarimetry, with a current research focus on radio galaxies and machine learning. Member of the POSSUM, QUOCKA, and EMU collaborations. Experience in observing (e.g. ATCA), data reduction (e.g. CASA), and data analysis (e.g. Python), working with Square Kilometre Array pathfinder telescopes. Communicating science, particularly astronomy, through a variety of outreach (presentations, demonstrations) and media (television, podcasting, and radio).

Research Experience ____

University of Manchester

RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

OCTOBER 2021 - PRESENT

MANCHESTER, UK

- Working on the polarisation properties of well-resolved radio galaxies in the POSSUM (Polarisation Sky Survey of the Universe's Magnetism) Pilot Surveys.
- Previously: machine learning for radio astronomy: building machine learning datasets from the ASKAP telescope EMU survey Zooniverse data, using specialist data selection, extraction and formatting (6 months).

PhD student; Supervisors: Dr. Patrick Leahy & Prof. Anna Scaife

SEPTEMBER 2017 - SEPTEMBER 2021

- Member of the POSSUM collaboration, focusing on magnetic fields around well-resolved radio galaxies.
- Analysis of large polarisation data cubes from the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder telescope (ASKAP) via extensive use of programming languages (e.g. Python) and astronomical software (e.g. CASA) in both Linux and MacOSX environments.
- Observing with the Australia Telescope Compact Array (ATCA): proposal writing (as PI & Co-I), observation planning and supervising, reduction and analysis of data in Miriad.

MASTERS STUDENT; SUPERVISORS: PROF. ANNA SCAIFE, DR. DAVID MULCAHY, DR. JUSTIN BRAY

SEPTEMBER 2016 - JUNE 2017

• Project title: Magnetic Structures in the Spiral Galaxy NGC 628. Calibration and imaging of C, L, and X-band data from the Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array (JVLA) in CASA, and subsequent analysis of Faraday rotation maps with Python scripts.

SUMMER STUDENT; SUPERVISOR: DR. JUSTIN BRAY

JUNE 2016 - JULY 201

• Project title: Radio pulses from the star CU Virginis. Reduction and analysis of ATCA data of the magnetically chemically peculiar star CU Virginis in Miriad. Imaging of radio pulses from the star in CASA, and spectrographic analysis of the results via Python.

SUMMER STUDENT; SUPERVISOR: DR. PATRICK LEAHY

JUNE 2015 - AUGUST 2015

• Solar sidelobe analysis for the C-Band All Sky Survey (C-BASS). Improved existing models of sidelobes and solar variability using IDL, Python and MATLAB.

Netherlands Institute for Radio Astronomy (ASTRON)

DWINGELOO, NETHERLANDS

SUMMER STUDENT; SUPERVISOR: DR. JESS BRODERICK

JUNE 2017 - SEPTEMBER 2017

• Project title: Recombination line science with SKA precursor technology - a search towards the Galactic Centre with the Engineering Development Array (EDA). Normalisation and stacking of uncalibrated data from an exploratory scan by the EDA, to obtain detections of carbon and hydrogen Radio Recombination Lines (RRLs).

Publications

REFEREED

- 2. T. D. Joseph, M. D. Filipović, E. J. Crawford, I. Bojičić, **E. L. Alexander** et al., **The ASKAP-EMU Early Science Project: Radio Continuum Survey of the Small Magellanic Cloud**. MNRAS 490, 1, 1202-1219 (2019).
- 1. J. B. R. Oonk, E. L. Alexander, J. Broderick, M. Sokolowski, and R. Wayth, Spectroscopy with the Engineering Development Array: cold H+ at 63 MHz towards the Galactic center. MNRAS 487, 4, p. 4737–4750 (2019).

IN REVIEW & IN PREP.

- 6. G. Segal, [4 others], E. L. Alexander et al., Identifying anomalous sources in the EMU Pilot Survey data using a complexity-based approach. Submitted to MNRAS (2022). https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.14677
- 5. M. M. Boyce, [21 others], E. L. Alexander et al., Hydra II: Characterisation of Aegean, Caesar, ProFound, PyBDSF, and Selavy source finders. Submitted to PASA (2022).
- M. M. Boyce, [21 others], E. L. Alexander et al., Hydra I: An extensible multi-source-finder comparison and cataloguing tool. Submitted to PASA (2022).
- 3. M. Cárcamo, A. M. M. Scaife, E. L. Alexander and J. P. Leahy, CS-ROMER: A novel compressed sensing framework for Faraday depth reconstruction. Submitted to MNRAS (2022). https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.01413
- 2. B. M. Gaensler, [others], E. L. Alexander et al., The Polarisation Sky Survey of the Universe's Magnetism (POSSUM). I. Science Goals and Survey Description To be submitted to PASA (2022).
- 1. M. Bowles, H. Tang, E. Vardoulaki, E. L. Alexander et al., Radio Galaxy Zoo EMU: Towards a Semantically Meaningful Morphology Taxonomy. To be submitted to MNRAS (2022).

Education

| Luucation | |
|---|----------------|
| University of Manchester | Manchester, UK |
| PhD in Astrophysics | 2017 – 2022 |
| • Project: Magnetic Fields around Radio Galaxies (see research experience). | |
| MPHYS IN PHYSICS WITH ASTROPHYSICS (FIRST CLASS HONOURS) | 2013 - 2017 |
| • Masters Project: Magnetic Structures in the Spiral Galaxy NGC 628 (see research experience). | |
| Huntington School | York, UK |
| A-Levels and GCSEs | 2006-2013 |
| • A-Levels: Physics (A*); Chemistry (A*); Biology (A*); Mathematics (A*); Further Mathematics (A); General Studies (A). | |

• GCSEs: 13 A* - A, including English and Mathematics.

Observing & Sucessful Proposals _

PI: Australia Telescope Compact Array, 2019APRS, A polarised look at extended DRAGNs in Ophiuchus (C3315, 40 hours). Co-I: Australia Telescope Compact Array, 2018APRS/2018OCTS/2019APRS/2020APRS, The QUOCKA Survey (Pl: G. Heald, C3244, 830 hours total). Personal observing contribution: 10 sessions totalling 65 hours, on-site & remote. Co-I: e-MERLIN ToO Request, Supernova SN 2013ei (PI: H. Rampadarath, 13 hours, 2017).

Awards & Funding _____

| Fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society (FRAS), London, UK | 2016 – pres. |
|---|--------------|
| COVID funding extension (6 months), University of Manchester | 2021 |
| George Rigg Studentship (3.5 years), Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics | 2017 - 2021 |
| President's Doctoral Scholarship (3 years), University of Manchester | 2017 - 2020 |
| Summer Studentship funding (10 weeks), SKA Organisation & ASTRON | 2017 |
| Summer Studentship funding (6 weeks), University of Manchester | 2016 |
| Undergraduate achievement award , University of Manchester | 2013 |
| Presentations | |
| Invited | |
| Magnetic fields around radio galaxies with POSSUM, Curtin University colloquium (remote). | 2021 |

| Radio Astronomy & Astrophysical Magnetism, North American Foundation Awards for Postgraduate Study at the | 2020 |
|---|------|
| University of Manchester (NAFUM) board meeting (remote). | 2020 |
| A Tour through the Radio Universe, York Astronomical Society (remote). | 2020 |
| A Tour through the Radio Universe, Derby & District Astronomical Society. | 2019 |

Cosmic Magnetism, York Astronomical Society. 2018

CONTRIBUTED

Rotation Measure maps of Radio Galaxies with ASKAP, SPARCS X conference, remote. 2021 Magnetic fields around radio galaxies with POSSUM, Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, internal seminar. 2021 Magnetic fields around radio galaxies with POSSUM, 'A precursor view of the SKA Sky' conference, remote. 2021 Magnetic fields around Ophiuchus radio galaxies with POSSUM, Poster, 'New Science enabled by New 2019

Technologies in the SKA Era' conference. Radio Astronomy & Astrophysical Magnetism, Multiple occasions. 2018 - 2020 Recombination line science with SKA precursor technology., Astrolunch, ASTRON, Dwingeloo, Netherlands. 2017

Teaching & Supervising _____

| Associate Fellow of the Higher Education Academy (AFHEA), | 2020 – pres |
|--|-------------|
| Demonstrator, 2nd Year Undergraduate Laboratory , University of Manchester, UK | 2018 - 2021 |
| Examination Invigilator , University of Manchester, UK | 2018 |
| Demonstrator, 1st Year Undergraduate Laboratory , University of Manchester, UK | 2017 |
| Peer Assisted Study Sessions (PASS) Leader & Peer Mentor, University of Manchester, UK | 2014 - 2016 |

| Laboratory togeting committee. Don't of Dhysics & Astronomy, University of Manahastay III/ | 2020 202 |
|--|-------------------|
| Laboratory teaching committee, Dept. of Physics & Astronomy, University of Manchester, UK | 2020 – 202 |
| Postgraduate representative, Dept. of Physics & Astronomy, University of Manchester, UK | 2018 – 202 202 |
| PhD interviews support team ,Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, University of Manchester Local Organising Committee: Internal Symposium ,Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, University of Manchester | |
| Local Organising Committee: A Centenary of Astrophysical Jets conference, SKAO HQ, Cheshire, UK | 201 |
| Laboratory open day tour guide, University of Manchester, UK | 201 |
| Internal Seminar organiser,Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, University of Manchester, UK | 2017 – 201 |
| Postgraduate committee, Jodrell Bank Centre for Astrophysics, University of Manchester, UK | 2017 - 201 |
| Astronomy Society Committee, (Science Officer; then Chair; then Secretary), University of Manchester, UK | 2017 - 201 |
| Physics Netball team, Captain, University of Manchester, UK | 2015 – 201 |
| UCAS interview day help, School of Physics & Astronomy, University of Manchester, UK | 2015 – 201 |
| The first of the second of the | 2013 20. |
| Selected Media & Outreach | |
| TELEVISION | |
| Breakfast, BBC One, Multiple live apperances (in-studio and remote) to discuss astronomy news. Topics included | 2018 – 202 |
| Oumuamua, New Horizons, Chang'e 4, and the Perseid meteor shower. | 2010 20 |
| Newsround, CBBC, Pre-recorded segment on astronomy. https://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/49911516 | 20: |
| BBC News & BBC World News , Multiple remote live apperance; topics included lunar eclipse and New Horizons | 20: |
| probe. | 20. |
| Radio & podcasting | |
| The Jodcast , Producing, presenting, interviewing, and audio editing of a popular astronomy podcast. | 2017 - 202 |
| BBC Radio 5 Live , Monthly (Jan – Sept 2018) discussion of recent astrophysical news and the night sky. One-off | 2018 – 20 |
| features on a range of topics, including: Jupiter opposition, Jodrell Bank UNESCO award, and Betelgeuse dimming. | |
| BBC World Service OS, Explaining the physics of the "broom challenge". | 202 |
| BBC Radio 5 Live, Discussion panel: this year & next in space. | 20: |
| Press Releases & articles | |
| The Conversation , "A 4G network on the Moon is bad news for radio astronomy" | 202 |
| ASTRON press release, "Star formation may be halted by cold ionised hydrogen" CONSULTING | 20: |
| CBBC Newsround, Various articles and features including https://www.bbc.co.uk/newsround/59559445 | 2020 – 202 |
| Netflix: Night on Earth, Consultant for astronomy content (episode: Moonlit Plains). | 2019 – 202 |
| BBC News, Feature on how Wi-Fi works. | 20: |
| Online talks & workshops | |
| Everything Astronomy: An overview of the science & what it can do for you., Young Professionals Society webinar | 202 |
| UK Moonsightling Live, New Crescent Society Facebook Live video, host & astronomy features. | 202 |
| The Science of the New Crescent Moon, New Crescent Society online workshop. EVENTS | 202 |
| Bluedot Festival, Jodrell Bank Observatory, Cheshire, UK. Science explanations and talk introductions. | 2016 - 20 |
| ScienceX, Trafford Centre, Manchester, UK. Science busking. | 201 |
| , | _0. |

References _______
Available on request

SCHOOLS

2016

2015

2019

2015

2014-2015

2011 - 2013

2018 - 2019

Platform for Investigation, Museum of Science and Industry (MOSI), Manchester, UK.

British Science Festival Fringe, Bradford, West Yorkshire, UK. Science busking.

Physics in the Field volunteer for the Institute of Physics, Various locations.

INFUSE, University of Manchester, UK. Physics workshops for Year 10 and Year 12.

ISOLDE Lego Mindstorms Workshops, University of Manchester, Manchester, UK.

Workshop: Journey through the Solar System, Chapel Street Primary School, Manchester, UK.

Stargazing Live event: public astronomy demonstrations, York, UK.